<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="BBC">
            <hyperlink>http://www.bbc.com/news/election-us-2016-37920175</hyperlink>
            <titleLine>US election 2016 result: Trump beats Clinton to take White House</titleLine>
            <section>US Election 2016</section>
            <pubInfo>
                <date>9 November 2016</date>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head> Media caption'I will be president for all Americans'<media/>
    <body>
        <p>Donald Trump will become the 45th US president after a <emo type="adj">stunning</emo>
            victory over Democrat Hillary Clinton.</p>
        <p>The Republican said he would serve all Americans and called for the country to unite,
            following a divisive campaign which saw him beset by controversies.</p>
        <p>Hillary Clinton is due to appear in New York for her first public statement since
            conceding to Mr Trump in a telephone call on Tuesday evening.</p>
        <p>Outgoing President Barack Obama has congratulated his successor by phone.</p>
        <p>Mr Obama invited Mr Trump to a meeting at the White House on Thursday to discuss the
            transition.</p>
        <p>When Mr Trump is sworn in as president in January, he will have the benefit of a
            Republican majority in both houses of Congress, as <a
                href="http://www.bbc.com/news/election-us-2016-37917345">the party unexpectedly
                retained control</a> of both the Senate and the House of Representatives.</p>
        <p>The Republican nominee <emo type="verb">defied</emo> pre-election polling to claim swing
            states, <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/election/us2016/results">winning the key
                battlegrounds</a> of Florida, Ohio and Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The president-elect told cheering supporters that Americans must now <quote>bind the
                wounds of division</quote>, after a <emo type="adj">gruelling</emo>, <emo type="adj"
                >acrimonious</emo> electoral battle.</p>
        <p><quote>I want to tell the world community that while we will always put America's
                interests first, we will deal fairly with everyone,</quote> he said.</p>
        <p>Global markets fell <emo type="adv">sharply</emo> at the news, but later recovered.</p>
        <p>House Speaker Paul Ryan paid tribute to his fellow Republican, saying he had
                <quote>turned politics on its head</quote> and would lead a unified Republican
            government.</p>
        <p>Around the world, leaders and the media have been reacting to America's election <emo
                type="noun">upset</emo>:</p>
        <p>Germany's foreign minister said the outcome would make things <quote>more
                difficult</quote>, with US foreign policy <quote>less predictable</quote></p>
        <p>Russian President Vladimir Putin - for whom Mr Trump has voiced support but who Democrats
            accused of election meddling - said he hoped ties could improve from their current
                <quote>critical condition</quote></p>
        <p>The European Union said close co-operation with the US was the only way to deal with
                <quote>unprecedented challenges</quote> around the world</p>
        <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-politics-37921086">British Prime Minister Theresa May
            said the UK and the US had an <quote>enduring and special relationship</quote></a> and
        would remain close partners on trade, security and defence <subHead>'United
            people'</subHead>
        <p>While US media report that Mrs Clinton is slightly ahead in the popular vote, in the US
            electoral college system which determines the presidency, <a
                href="http://www.bbc.com/news/election-us-2016-37249697">what matters is winning
                individual states.</a></p>
        <p>As poll counting went late into the night, it was Mr Trump's <emo type="adj">shock</emo>
            victory in Wisconsin that put him over the 270 out of 538 electoral college votes needed
            to win the White House.</p>
        <p>Minutes after Mrs Clinton called him to concede, the US president-elect took to the stage
            with his family at his victory rally in a New York hotel ballroom and paid tribute to
            his <emo type="noun">rival</emo>.</p>
        <p><quote>Hillary has worked very long and very hard over a long period of time, and we owe
                her a major debt of gratitude for her service to our country.</quote></p>
        <p>He called for Americans to <quote>come together as one united people</quote> and <emo
                type="verb">pledged</emo> to be president <quote>for all Americans</quote>, after a
            campaign that saw him <emo type="verb">hit</emo> out at Muslims, Hispanics and other
            minority groups.</p>
        <subHead>'Popular revolution': By Anthony Zurcher, BBC News, Washington</subHead>
        <p>Donald Trump <emo type="verb">defied</emo> all expectations from the very start of his
            presidential campaign more than a year ago.</p>
        <p>Very few people thought he would actually run. He did. They thought he wouldn't climb in
            the polls. He did. They said he wouldn't win any primaries. He did. They said he could
            never overcome resistance from the Republican establishment and win his party's
            nomination. He did.</p>
        <p>Finally, they said there was no way he could compete for, let alone win, a general
            election match-up with Hillary Clinton. Now he's President-elect Trump.</p>
        <p>He staged the most unconventional of campaigns, running on gut instinct and his trademark
                <emo type="noun">bombast</emo> when others - both within his own party and outside -
            counselled moderation and a pivot to positions perceived to be more acceptable to
            mainstream voters.</p>
        <p>He stayed true to the methods and tactics that got him to the cusp of the presidency, and
            in the end he was rewarded for it.</p>
        <p>Down the stretch Mr Trump <emo type="verb">boasted</emo> that he was leading a movement,
            riding the crest of a popular <emo type="noun">revolution</emo> that would change the
            face of American politics. He was right.</p>
        <p>Mr Trump has so far won 28 US states. Mrs Clinton, 69, has only notched up victories in
            18 US states and the District of Columbia.</p>
        <p>New Hampshire and Michigan remained too close to call as of Wednesday morning.</p>
        <p>Mr Trump held solidly Republican territory, despite <emo type="adv">vigorous</emo>
            Democrat campaigning in states such as Georgia, Arizona and Utah, and achieved <emo
                type="adj">major</emo>
            <emo type="noun">upsets</emo> in swing states, winning Pennsylvania and Wisconsin,
            states that have not supported a Republican presidential candidate since 1988 and 1984
            respectively.</p>
        <p>At 70, the billionaire will be the oldest first-term president in US history.</p>
        <subHead>How Trump won in maps</subHead>
        <p>Mrs Clinton, who <emo type="verb">dreamed</emo> of becoming the first female US
            president, did not appear at what was meant to be her victory rally in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr Trump provoked controversy on the campaign trail for comments about women, Muslims and
            a plan to build a wall along the US-Mexican border.</p>
        <p>He <emo type="verb">fired</emo> up white, working-class American voters who were angry at
            the Washington establishment and felt left behind by globalisation.</p>
        <p>Mrs Clinton - who held a slim lead in opinion polls going into the vote - saw her
            campaign <emo type="verb">dogged</emo> by FBI investigations into her use of a private
            email server as US secretary of state. Last Sunday, the FBI cleared her once again of
            any criminality.</p>
        <p>Mr Trump's campaign manager Kellyanne Conway told CNN that Mr Trump had not discussed the
            issue of prosecuting Mrs Clinton in her concession phone call.</p>
        <p>Polls showed she won support from female, African American and Hispanic voters, while Mr
            Trump scored well with male and white voters.</p>
        <p>In a separate development, Massachusetts, Nevada and California <a
                href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-37917472">voted to legalise
                recreational marijuana</a>, which could lead to the creation of the largest market
            for marijuana products in the US.</p>
    </body>
</article>
