<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../articleRefGuide/newsAnalysisRelax-NG.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="FOX">
            <hyperlink>http://www.foxnews.com/us/2017/01/21/hundreds-thousands-women-protest-against-trump.html</hyperlink>
            <section>politics</section>
            <titleLine>Hundreds of thousands of women protest against Trump</titleLine>
            <pubInfo>
                <date>2017-01-21</date>
                <time></time>
                <credit>
                    <author>Associated Press</author>
                </credit>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head>

    <body>
        <media/>
        <p><em>WASHINGTON</em> – Wearing pink, pointy-eared <q>pussyhats</q> to <emo type="verb">mock</emo> the new
            president, hundreds of thousands of women massed in the nation's capital and cities
            around the globe Saturday to send Donald Trump an <emo type="adj">emphatic</emo> message that they won't let
            his agenda go unchallenged over the next four years.</p>
        <p><quote>We march today for the moral core of this nation, against which our new president
                is waging a war,</quote> actress America Ferrera told the Washington crowd.
                <quote>Our dignity, our character, our rights have all been under attack and a
                platform of hate and division assumed power yesterday. But the president is not
                America. ... We are America and we are here to stay.</quote></p>
        <p>The women <emo type="verb">brandished</emo> signs with messages such as <q>Women won't back down</q> and <q>Less
                fear more love</q> and <emo type="verb">decried</emo> Trump's stand on such issues as abortion, health
            care, diversity and climate change. The message <emo type="verb">reverberated</emo> at demonstrations around
            the globe, from Paris and Berlin to Sydney and beyond.</p>
        <p>There were early signs that the crowds in Washington could top those that gathered for
            Trump's inauguration on Friday. City officials said organizers of the Women's March on
            Washington more than doubled their turnout estimate to 500,000 as crowds began <emo type="verb">swelling</emo>
            and subways into the city became <emo type="verb">clogged</emo> with participants.</p>
        <p>It wasn't just a Washington phenomenon and it wasn't just women: More than 600 <q>sister
                marches</q> were planned across the country and around the world, and plenty of men
            were part of the <emo type="noun">tableau</emo>, too. Organizers estimated 3 million would march worldwide.</p>
        <p>As the rally alongside the National Mall took shape, Trump opened his first full day as
            president by attending a prayer service at the Washington National Cathedral, a
            tradition for the day after inauguration.</p>
        <p>Outside on the streets of Washington, feminist leader Gloria Steinem described the
            worldwide mobilization as <quote>the upside of the downside: This is an outpouring of
                energy and democracy like I have never seen in my very long life.</quote></p>
        <p><quote>Sometimes we must put our bodies where our beliefs are,</quote> she told the
            Washington crowd, labeling Trump an <q>impossible president.</q></p>
        <p>In Paris, thousands marched in the Eiffel Tower neighborhood in a <emo type="adj">joyful</emo> atmosphere,
            singing and carrying posters reading: <q>We have our eyes on you Mr. Trump</q> and
                <q>With our sisters in Washington.</q></p>
        <p>At a rally in Concord, New Hampshire, author Jodi Picoult said: <quote>We in New
                Hampshire are not in the habit of going in reverse. We have the backs of those who
                are less fortunate — who may be struggling for health care, for environmental
                rights, for racial equality, for a fair wage, for justice.</quote></p>
        <p>Hillary Clinton, who lost to Trump, took to Twitter to thank the participants for
                <quote>standing, speaking and marching for our values.</quote></p>
        <p>Retired teacher Linda Lastella, 69, who came to Washington from Metuchen, New Jersey,
            said she had never marched before but felt the need to speak out when <quote>many
                nations are experiencing this same kind of pullback and hateful, hateful
                attitudes.</quote></p>
        <p><quote>It just seemed like we needed to make a very firm stand of where we were,</quote>
            she said.</p>
        <p>Rose Wurm, 64, a retired medical secretary from Bedford, Pennsylvania, boarded a
            Washington-bound bus in Hagerstown, Maryland, at 7 a.m. carrying two signs: one asking
            Trump to stop tweeting, and one asking him to fix, not trash, the Obamacare health
            law.</p>
        <p><quote>There are parts of it that do need change. It's something new, something unique
                that's not going to be perfect right out of the gate,</quote> she said.</p>
        <p>Many wore hand-knit <q>pussyhats</q> — a message of female <emo type="noun">empowerment</emo> <emo type="verb">aimed</emo> squarely at
            Trump's <emo type="adv">crude</emo> <emo type="verb">boast</emo> about grabbing women's genitals.</p>
        <p>In Prague, hundreds gathered in Wenceslas Square in freezing weather, waving portraits of
            Trump and Russia's Vladimir Putin and holding banners that read <q>This is just the
                beginning,</q>
            <q>Kindness</q> and <q>Love.</q></p>
        <p><quote>We are worried about the way some politicians talk, especially during the American
                elections,</quote> said organizer Johanna Nejedlova.</p>
        <p>In Copenhagen, Denmark, march organizer Lesley-Ann Brown said: <quote>Nationalist, racist
                and misogynistic trends are growing worldwide and threaten the most marginalized
                groups in our societies including women, people of color, immigrants, Muslims, the
                LGBT community and people with disabilities.</quote></p>
        <p>In Sydney, thousands of Australians marched in <emo type="noun">solidarity</emo> in Hyde Park. One organizer
            said hatred, bigotry and racism are not only America's problems.</p>
        <p>The idea for the women's march took off after a number of women posted on social media in
            the hours after Trump's election about the need to <emo type="verb">mobilize</emo>. Hundreds of groups quickly
            joined the cause, pushing a wide range of causes, including abortion rights, gun
            control, climate change and immigrant rights.</p>
        <p>While the march organizers' <q>mission and vision</q> statement never mentions Trump and
            stresses broad themes, including the message that <q>women's rights are human
                rights,</q> the unifying factor among those turning out appeared to be a <emo type="noun">loathing</emo>
            for the new president and <emo type="noun">dismay</emo> that so much of the country voted for him.</p>
        <p>Friday's unrest during the inauguration led police to use pepper spray and stun grenades
            to prevent the <emo type="noun">chaos</emo> from spilling into Trump's formal procession and the evening balls.
            About a mile from the National Mall, police gave chase to a group of about 100
            protesters who <emo type="verb">smashed</emo> the windows of downtown businesses, including a Starbucks, a Bank
            of America and a McDonald's, as they <emo type="verb">denounced</emo> capitalism and Trump.</p>
    </body>
</article>
