<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../articleRefGuide/newsAnalysisRelax-NG.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="CNN">
            <hyperlink>http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/politics/womens-march-wrap/</hyperlink>
            <section>politics</section>
            <titleLine>Protesters across globe rally for women's rights</titleLine>
            <pubInfo>
                <date when="2017-01-21">2017-01-21</date>
                <time value="10:52:00">10:52 PM ET</time>
                <credit>
                    <author>Ralph Ellis</author>
                </credit>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head>

    <body>
        <media>Women's Marches around the world 01:03</media>
        <p><em>(CNN)-</em>More than one million people marched through Washington, D.C., and other
            American cities Saturday to show support for women's rights and express their <emo type="noun">discontent</emo>
            over the election of President Donald Trump.</p>
        <p>The Women's March drew members of Congress, world-famous actresses and <emo type="adj">countless</emo> citizens
            like Joanne Gascoyne of Albany, New York a 78-year-old retired teacher who traveled to
            New York City with her daughter and two granddaughters.</p>
        <p><quote sex="f" pol="u_dem">I feel people are afraid to vote for a woman for president,</quote>Gascoyne
            said.<quote sex="f" pol="u_dem">I'm really here for women and to inspire my granddaughters to carry
                on.</quote></p>
        <p>The protesters came out for a range of reasons, including immigration, health care and a
            general <emo type="noun">antipathy</emo> to Trump. But most said they wanted to show support for women and
            <emo type="verb">feared</emo> that there will be <emo type="noun">attacks</emo> on women's rights during Trump's presidency.</p>
        <p>CNN did not make its own crowd estimates, but <a
                href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/politics/sean-spicer-fact-check/index.html"
                >compiled official estimates from law enforcement agencies</a> for many of the
            <q>sister marches</q> around the country that drew large crowds. The million-person count
            doesn't include the thousands of people who took part in the Women's March on Washington
            for which there was no official crowd estimate.</p>
        <p>Marches were also held in cities around the world.</p>
        <p>The biggest demonstration took place in Washington, where protesters filled Pennsylvania
            Avenue, the same street Trump walked down a day before during his inaugural parade. In
            the evening, the crowd moved toward the White House.</p>
        <p>On the mall, filmmaker Michael Moore, feminist icon Gloria Steinem, musician Alicia Keys
            and other speakers <emo type="adv">emotionally</emo> <emo type="verb">attacked</emo> Trump for his views on immigration, Muslims and
            women.</p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/politics/womens-march-speeches/index.html">What
                celebrities and activists had to say</a>
        </p>
        <p><quote sex="f" pol="dem">It took this horrific moment of darkness to wake us the f--k up,</quote> Madonna
            told the crowd. <quote sex="f" pol="dem">It seems as though we had all slipped into a false sense of
                comfort, that justice would prevail and that good would win in the end.</quote></p>
        <p>Historian Douglas Brinkley told CNN that people will always remember the inauguration and
            the march as momentous events.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="u_dem">It's big. It's a huge moment,</quote> Brinkley said. <quote sex="m" pol="u_dem">It also reminded me,
                believe it or not, of V-J Day, Victory Over Japan Day, 1945. Because when victory
                came people started coming out of apartments and homes ... a lot of extra people in
                these towns just started coming out.</quote></p>

            <subHead>Marches across America</subHead>

        <p>March organizers said protests took place in more than 600 cities across the world.</p>
        <p>Attendance was not always easy to determine. For instance, Washington march organizers
            said about 500,000 people took part, but authorities did not confirm that number or
            provide their own estimate.</p>
        <p>In Boston, 120,000 to 125,000 people protested, according to a police aerial photo
            analysis cited by a senior Boston Police official. Police said the crowd there was too
            big for the march route and could not proceed because <q>it would be like a snake
                eating its tail.</q></p>
        <p>U.S. Sen. Elizabeth Warren urged Boston protesters to resist: <quote sex="f" pol="dem">We can whimper. We can
                whine. Or we can fight back! We come here to stand shoulder to shoulder to make
                clear: We are here! We will not be silent! We will not play dead! We will fight for
                what we believe in!</quote></p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/20/politics/pussyhat-project-washington-march-trnd/">Pussyhat Project tops off Women's March on Washington</a>
        </p>
        <p>In Los Angeles, more than 100,000 people marched, police said. So many people crammed
            into the streets that <quote sex="f" pol="u_dem">our march turned into a stand,</quote> said Ellen Crafts, who handled
            public relations for the event.</p>
        <media>Photos:Women's March on Washington</media>
        <p>Demonstrators in New York City marched toward Trump Tower -- the President's main
            residence when he's not in the White House -- but were blocked at Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>Police said 20,000 people protested in Houston, 60,000 in Oakland. In Atlanta, 60,000
            people marched with US Rep. John Lewis, a major Trump critic.</p>
        <p>CNN could not independently confirm any of these crowd estimates.</p>
        <p>Overall, the protesters were law-abiding, with police reporting only four arrests in 21
            American cities. Nobody was arrested in Washington.</p>
        <p>Protests even in Antarctica</p>
        <p><q>Sister marches</q> happened outside the United States, too.</p>
        <p>People gathered to demonstrate in most major cities around the world, including London;
            Tel Aviv; Melbourne, Australia; Pristina, Kosovo; Moscow; Berlin and Mexico City --
            often in front of US embassies.</p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/europe/london-womens-march">London marches for
                <q>hope not hate</q></a>
        </p>
        <p>In Athens, Greece, protesters included refugees from Elliniko Camp, located in the old
            Athens airport.</p>
        <p>There was <a
                href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/politics/womens-march-antarctica/index.html"
                >even a protest in Antarctica</a> -- about 30 eco-minded tourists and non-government
            scientists aboard a ship in international waters hoisted signs saying <q>Penguins for
            peace</q> and <q>Seals for science,</q> organizers said.</p>
        <p>
            <a
                href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/opinions/women-rallying-cry-rowe-finkbeiner-opinion/index.html"
                >A rallying <emo type="noun">cry</emo> for women</a>
        </p>
        
            <subHead>Bigger than inaugural?</subHead>
        
        <p>The march organizers believe more people came out Saturday for the protests than for
            Trump's inaugural events on Friday.</p>
        <p>Washington protest organizers, who originally sought a permit for a gathering of 200,000,
            said Saturday that as many as a half million people participated, <emo type="verb">dwarfing</emo> Friday's
            inaugural crowd.</p>
        <p>
            <a
                href="http://money.cnn.com/2017/01/21/media/sean-spicer-press-secretary-statement/index.html"
                >White House secretary <emo type="verb">attacks</emo> media</a>
        </p>
        <p>More than 470,000 people had taken the Metro, the Washington subway system, by 1 p.m., a
            weekend ridership record. The metro tweeted Saturday there were 275,000 trips taken
            Saturday by 11 a.m.</p>
        <p>By comparison, on Friday, there were 193,000 trips by 11 a.m., according to Metro.</p>
        <p>Not everyone agrees. Trump, <a
                href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/politics/trump-presidency-day-two/index.html">in
                his first speech after the Inauguration</a>, said the media under-counted the size
            of the crowd for his Friday swearing-in ceremony.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">I get up this morning, I turn on one of the networks, and they show an empty
                field. I'm like, wait a minute. I made a speech. I looked out, the field was, it
                looked like a million, million and a half people. They showed a field where there
                were practically nobody standing there. And they said, Donald Trump did not draw
                well,</quote> the President said.</p>
        <p>Trump said the unnamed network reported he drew 250,000 people.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">Now, that's not bad,</quote> Trump said. <quote sex="m" pol="rep">But it's a lie,</quote> adding
            that the inauguration drew significantly more than 250,000 people.</p>
        <p>Later Saturday, <a
                href="http://money.cnn.com/2017/01/21/media/sean-spicer-press-secretary-statement/index.html"
                >White House Press Secretary Sean Spicer called his first press briefing</a> and
            questioned the media's reporting on crowd sizes, saying the Trump inauguration was
            <quote sex="m" pol="rep">the largest audience to ever witness an inauguration, period.</quote></p>
        <p>But Metro confirms numbers first reported in the Washington Post showing that 570,557
            riders took trips between the subway system's opening at 4 a.m. Friday through its
            closing at midnight.</p>
        <p>The numbers are lower than what the system saw in 2009 and 2013 during Obama's
            inaugurations: 1.1 million trips in 2009 and 782,000 in 2013.</p>
        
            <subHead><q>Strength in numbers</q></subHead>
        
        <p>The protesters, which included many men, hit the streets for different reasons, among
            them health care, the future of the Affordable Care Act, the environment and income
            equality.</p>
        <p>But Trump's stated attitudes toward women and his comments about judging women by their
            weight and appearance kept coming up, as did <a
                href="http://www.cnn.com/videos/politics/2016/10/07/donald-trump-audio-comments-wapo-report-keilar-lead.cnn"
                >his now infamous remarks about grabbing women by their genitalia</a>.</p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/politics/womens-march-highlights/index.html"
                >Women's March: <emo type="adj">Cathartic</emo> moment or <emo type="adj">enduring</emo> movement?</a>
        </p>
        <p><quote sex="f" pol="u_dem">That's just something that really angers me, and I don't think it has any place in
            my world,</quote> Maeve Kelly, 25 of Lambertville, New Jersey. <quote sex="f" pol="u_dem">It feels like
                everything we have worked toward, and all that suffragettes worked toward -- so we
                could vote and be successful -- is threatened now.</quote></p>
        <p>Leaders and activists from hundreds of left-leaning groups joined the march, including
            the NAACP, Planned Parenthood, the American Federation of Teachers, as well as
            pro-immigrant and pro-environment groups.</p>
        <p>
            <a
                href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/us/canadians-rejected-border-womens-march/index.html"
                >Canadians say they were turned away at border</a>
        </p>
        <p>Margaret Huang, the executive director of Amnesty International USA, which co-sponsored
            the Washington march, said the group's members were concerned about talk of a Muslim
            registry.</p>
        <p><quote sex="f" pol="u_dem">These sorts of rhetorical commitments that (Trump) made on the campaign trail
                cannot become policy,</quote> she said.</p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/21/politics/womens-march-signs-trnd-irpt/index.html"
                >Signs make a statement at Women's March</a>
        </p>
        <p>The protesters said the size of the crowds made a statement in itself.</p>
        <p><quote sex="f" pol="u_dem">It's important to show strength in numbers,</quote> said Jennifer Turney of
            Weathersfield, Vermont, who traveled to Boston to march with three friends. <quote sex="f" pol="u_dem">We're
                standing up for everyone's rights.</quote></p>
    </body>
        <foot>CNN's Maeve Reston, Ray Sanchez, Eric Levenson and Miguel Marquez contributed to this
            report.</foot>

</article>
