<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="NPR">
            <hyperlink>http://www.npr.org/2017/01/21/510991284/mothers-daughters-sisters-and-men-unite-to-protest-trumps-presidency</hyperlink>
            <section>around the nation</section>
            <titleLine>Mothers, Daughters, Sisters And Men Unite To Protest Trump's
                Presidency</titleLine>
            <pubInfo>
                <date>2017-01-21</date>
                <time>7:46 PM ET</time>
                <credit>
                    <author>Sarah McCammon</author>
                </credit>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head>

    <body>
        <media>Heather Ba, pictured here with her 4-year-old son, said she came from her home in
            Chapel Hill, N.C. with four generations of her family to participate in the Women's
            March in Washington, D.C.</media>
        <p>Donald Trump's first day in office has been marked by much of the same discord that
            characterized his campaign.</p>
        <p>In the hours after his inauguration, the newly sworn-in President began some of the work
            of governing – even as hundreds of thousands of people gathered in cities across the
            country, and around the world, to protest Trump's presidency.</p>
        <subHead>Women descend on Washington</subHead>
        <p>Many women brought their families to the main Women's March in Washington, D.C., which
            began with a rally with the U.S. Capitol in the background. Heather Ba from Chapel Hill,
            N.C., said she came with four generations of her family, including her own 4-year-old
            son.</p>
        <media>Erika Abril (R) and daughters Maria Emilia Proano, 18 (L) and Maria Paula Proano, 16
            (Center) at the Women's March Saturday.</media>
        <p><quote>We came to show our disapproval of our new president, and I think also to draw
                attention to women's issues,</quote> Ba said.</p>
        <p>She said she believes President Trump to be <quote>psychologically unwell and not fit to
                be president,</quote> and said she was considering becoming more involved in local
            politics during the next few years.</p>
        <p>Erika Abril came to Washington from Leesburg, VA., with her two teenage daughters.</p>
        <p><quote>"I just want them to be part of this – making history,</quote> she said.</p>
        <p>The family is originally from Ecuador, Abril said, and she's alarmed by some of Trump's
            rhetoric about immigrants and minorities.</p>
        <p><quote>It's just hard to be out of a country that sometimes you don't like what is
                happening in there, and then coming here thinking that everything's gonna be okay,
                and then not knowing what is going to come,</quote> she said. <quote>That is the
                hardest part.</quote></p>
        <p>Abril and her daughters held a sign that read, in Spanish, <quote>Respect my existence or
                expect my resistance.</quote></p>
        <media>The Apgar family: The mother Ruth (center) is flanked by daughters Kristina (L) and
            Samantha (R) at the Women's March on Saturday in Washington, D.C.</media>
        <p>Her 18-year-old daughter, Maria Emilia Proano, expressed frustration and disbelief that
            such a march felt necessary.</p>
        <p>
            <quote>We shouldn't be doing this, because we should already be equal to men and
                everything.</quote>
        </p>
        <subHead>Mothers, daughters, and sisters</subHead>
        <p>They were far from the only multigenerational family at the March.</p>
        <p>Kristina Apgar, 31, came from Brooklyn, New York to march with her mother, Ruth Apgar,
            and 25-year-old sister, Samantha Apgar, who lives in Connecticut.</p>
        <p><quote>I would be here no matter what by myself, but the fact that my mom and my sister
                are here and we're all united fighting for women's rights and inclusivity for all
                Americans, it means so much more,</quote> Kristina Apgar said.</p>
        <media>Eugene Beckley, a 28-year-old software designer from Ellicott City, Md., says he was
            thinking of his mother and female cousins when he came to the Women's March in
            Washington, D.C.</media>
        <p>Ruth Apgar remembers a time when she <q>put up with a lot in the workplace,</q> and she
            said she doesn't want her daughters to struggle like she did.</p>
        <p><quote>I'm not going back to the good old days, because quite frankly, they were not good
                old days for me,</quote> she said.</p>
        <subHead>Men, too</subHead>
        <p>While the crowd that filled the streets for multiple blocks was mostly female, there were
            men among the marchers.</p>
        <p>Eugene Beckley, a software developer from Ellicott City, MD., said he was thinking of his
            mother and female cousins when he came to the march. He said he's worried about the
            impact of Trump's administration on women's rights.</p>
        <media>Stefani Peart an 18-year-old from East Orange, N.J., is a student at George
            Washington University. She was among the protesters at the Women's March Saturday in
            Washington, D.C.</media>
        <p><quote>Feminism in general is only going to grow and be more supported by men supporting
                it,</quote> Beckley said.</p>
        <subHead>Not just women's issues</subHead>
        <p>While the Women's March was billed as a display of unity among people concerned about the
            tone set by the new administration, it hasn't been without internal conflicts. Women
            describing themselves as anti-abortion feminists have expressed disappointment about not
            being allowed to be official partners for the event, whose platform supports abortion
            rights.</p>
        <p>And concerns have surfaced about the representation and inclusion of minority women,
            prompting organizers to stress that the march was also a platform for demonstrators
            concerned about issues ranging from racial inequality to climate change.</p>
        <p>Stefani Peart, an African-American student at George Washington University from East
            Orange, N.J. said she felt the march ultimately succeeded at bringing diverse groups
            together.</p>
        <media>Arion Laws, 18, of Charleston, S.C., is a student at George Washington University.
            She says she attended the Women's March to send a message to President Donald Trump that
            his rhetoric is offensive.</media>
        <p>
            <quote>Being able to stand out here and see people of all races, all ethnicities come
                together to fight for the same common cause of just women's rights in general is
                something that needs to happen more often.</quote>
        </p>
        <p>
            <quote>And the fact that we're doing it right now just shows how [united] we are as a
                nation as much as Trump is trying to divide us.</quote>
        </p>
        <p>Her classmate, Arion Laws, is also African-American. The Charleston, S.C., native said
            she came to send Trump and his administration a message.</p>
        <p><quote>They've basically insulted every single minority,</quote> she said.</p>
        <p>Laws said she hoped the large crowds in Washington and across the country would send a
            message: <quote>I just want him and his administration to know that no, you can't
                silence us, and we won't be silenced.</quote></p>
        <subHead>Protests beyond the Beltway</subHead>
        <p>In addition to the main event in Washington, D.C., women and their supporters <a
                href="http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/01/21/510940708/womens-march-on-washington-goes-worldwide-snapshots-from-around-the-globe"
                >protested across the country and around the world.</a> Marches were held in several
            major European cities, Mexico, Thailand, and India, among other places. Protestors in
            the United States who couldn't make the trip to Washington organized their own hometown
            events. Thousands turned out in larger cities like Boston and Chicago, while many
            smaller cities like Sioux Falls, South Dakota, saw substantial turnouts given their
            size.</p>
        <subHead>President Trump starts working Friday, visits the CIA on Saturday</subHead>
        <p>As protestors marched through the streets of Washington, D.C.,Trump made an official
            visit to CIA Headquarters in Langley, VA., where he <a
                href="http://www.npr.org/2017/01/21/510977543/campaign-trail-trump-on-display-as-he-goes-to-cia-on-first-day-as-president"
                >praised the CIA, railed against the media, and talked up the size of the crowd at
                his inauguration</a>: <quote>a 20-block area, all the way up to the Washington
                Monument, was packed.</quote></p>
        <p>That's despite the fact that aerial photos of Trump's inauguration showed substantial
            empty space on the National Mall. In his first hours in office, Trump also took several
            official actions, including revamping the WhiteHouse.gov website and signing an
            executive order to <a
                href="http://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2017/01/21/510901402/trumps-executive-order-could-dismantle-parts-of-aca-before-replacement-is-ready"
                    ><q>minimize the economic burden</q> of the Affordable Care Act.</a></p>
        <p>Soon after Trump took office, the Justice Department requested and was <a
                href="http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/01/21/510952189/president-trumps-first-hours-in-office"
                >granted the delay</a> of two hearings on controversial issues; one involved a voter
            ID law in Texas, and the other was a hearing related to a police reform agreement in
            Baltimore.</p>
    </body>
</article>
