<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../articleRefGuide/newsAnalysisRelax-NG.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="BBC">
            <hyperlink>http://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-38705586</hyperlink>
            <section>US &amp; Canada</section>
            <titleLine>Donald Trump protests attract millions across US and world</titleLine>
            <pubInfo>
                <date>2017-01-21</date>
                <credit>
                    <author>no author</author> <!--SM do we want to do this or just take out the credit? -->
                </credit>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            <em>Millions of protesters have taken to the streets of cities in the US and around the
                globe to rally against the new US President Donald Trump.</em> <!-- SM some of our code uses em but most of it doesn't should we take it out? -->
        </p>
        <p>Larger numbers of demonstrators than expected turned out for more than 600 rallies
            worldwide.</p>
        <p>The aim was principally to highlight women's rights, which activists believe to be under
            <emo type="noun">threat</emo> from the new administration.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr Trump used his first full day in office to visit the CIA's HQ.</p>
        <p>He said he was <q>1,000%</q> behind the spy agency's employees and <a
                    href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-38707722">also <emo type="verb">accused</emo> the media
                    of being dishonest in its reporting of the size of the crowd at his
                    inauguration.</a></p>
        <p>Mr Trump did not refer to Saturday's protests.</p>
        
            <subHead><q>We are the majority</q></subHead>
        
        <p>The biggest US rally was in the capital Washington, which city officials estimated to be
            more than 500,000-strong.</p>
        <p>This <emo type= "adv">far</emo> <emo type="verb">exceeded</emo> the 200,000 that had originally been expected by organisers of the
            Women's March on Washington.</p>
        <p>By most estimates, it also surpassed the crowd at Friday's presidential inauguration.</p>
        <p>The protesters in the nation's capital heard speeches from Scarlett Johansson, Ugly Betty
            star America Ferrera, Ashley Judd, Gloria Steinem and Michael Moore among others.</p>
        <p>A planned march to the White House proved impossible as the entire route was filled with
            demonstrators.</p>
        <p>Interim DC Police Chief Peter Newsham told Associated Press: <quote>The crowd stretches
                so far that there's no room left to march.</quote></p>
        <p>
                <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/in-pictures-38703840">In pictures: Global marches
                    against Trump</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            
                <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-38700123">UK's marches against Trump</a>
            
        </p>
        <p>
            
                <a href="Obama leaves Democrats flailing in abyss">Obama leaves Democrats <emo type="verb">flailing</emo>
                    in <emo type="noun">abyss</emo></a>
            
        </p>
        <p>During his speech, Michael Moore ripped up a copy of the Washington Post, saying:
                <quote>The headline was 'Trump takes power'. I don't think so. Here's the power.
                Here's the majority of America right here. We are the majority.</quote></p>
        <p>The singer Madonna also made an appearance, swearing several times in a speech carried
            live by major US TV networks.</p>
        <p><quote>Yes, I am outraged. Yes, I have thought an awful lot about blowing up the White
                House,</quote> she said.</p>
        <p>America Ferrera told the crowd: <quote>We march today for the moral core of this nation,
                against which our new president is waging a war.</quote></p>
        <p>Huge crowds were reported at other US protests.</p>
        <p>So many turned out in Chicago - some 150,000 - that a planned march had to be called off
            and the event declared a rally. Streets were also <emo type="verb">overflowing</emo> in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p><emo type="adj">Huge</emo> crowds were also reported in New York, Seattle, Boston and Miami, some of the venues
            for about 300 nationwide protests.</p>
        <p>Many women wore knitted pink <q>pussy hats</q> - a reference to a recording that emerged
            during the election campaign in which Mr Trump talked about groping women.</p>
        
            <subHead><q>These are global problems</q></subHead>

        <p>Organisers of a London rally <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-38700123">said
                    between 80,000 and 100,000 people</a> had taken part there. Belfast,
            Cardiff, Edinburgh, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester and Bristol were among the other UK
            cities holding protests.</p>
        <p>Anti-Trump marches took place earlier in Australia, New Zealand and in several Asian
            cities.</p>
        <p>Several thousand women and men joined a rally in central Sydney, with a similar number in
            Melbourne.</p>
        <p>Women's March Sydney co-founder Mindy Freiband told the crowd: <quote>Hatred, hate
                speech, bigotry, discrimination, prejudicial policies - these are not American
                problems, these are global problems.</quote></p>
        <p>Barcelona, Rome, Amsterdam, Geneva, Budapest, Prague and Berlin were among the European
            cities that took part.</p>
        <p>In Paris, protester Francoise Seme Wallon said Mr Trump was <quote>a nasty guy and he's
                dangerous for the whole world</quote>.</p>
        <p>
            
                <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-38697653">Full text of
                    inauguration speech</a>
            
        </p>
        
            <subHead>Website overhaul</subHead>
        
        <p>Mr Trump's first full day in office began with an inter-faith service at Washington
            National Cathedral.</p>
        <p>He then visited the CIA's HQ in Langley, Virginia.</p>
        <p>In a speech there, he told about 400 employees: <quote>There is nobody who feels stronger
                about the intelligence community and the CIA than me.</quote></p>
        <p>During the election campaign, Mr Trump had <emo type="adv">sharply</emo> criticised the intelligence agencies
            over their stance on alleged Russian involvement.</p>
        <p>Mr Trump also talked up his yet-to-be-confirmed nominee for CIA chief, Mike Pompeo.</p>
        <p><quote>You will be getting a total gem,</quote> he told the employees.</p>
        <p>In one of his first steps, Mr Trump ordered government agencies to ease the <q>economic
                burden</q> of the health law known as Obamacare.</p>
        <p>His team also quickly <emo type="verb">overhauled</emo> the <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/">White
                    House website</a>. The revamp replaces Barack Obama's policies with Mr
            Trump's new agenda.</p>
        <p>The new administration lists only six issues on the website - energy, foreign policy,
            jobs and growth, military, law enforcement and trade deals.</p>
        <p>Critics <emo type="verb">complained</emo> that it made no mention of civil rights, healthcare, climate change or
            LGBT rights.</p>
        <p>
            
                <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-38637123">Eight ways Trump's
                    presidency makes history</a>
            
        </p>
        <p>
            
                <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/technology-38699809">Mild <emo type="noun">panic</emo> greets Trump
                    digital transition</a>
            
        </p>
        <p>
            
                <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-38695684">Trump's <emo type="adj">angry</emo> call to
                    arms</a>
            
        </p>
        <p>
            
                <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-38663043">Trump tracker: Can the
                    president deliver?</a>
            
        </p>
        <p>
            
                <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-38682568">What Trump supporters
                    want</a>
            
        </p>
    </body>
</article>
