<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../articleRefGuide/newsAnalysisRelax-NG.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="FOX">
            <hyperlink>http://www.foxbusiness.com/politics/2017/03/16/trump-weighs-legal-action-against-msnbc-reporter-over-tax-return-release.html</hyperlink>
            <section>politics</section>
            <titleLine>Trump Weighs Legal Action Against MSNBC, Reporter Over Tax Return
                Release</titleLine>
            <pubInfo>
                <date when="2017-03-16">2017-03-16</date>
                <credit>
                    <author>Brian Schwartz , Charlie Gasparino</author>
                </credit>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head>

    <body>
        <media>U.S. President Donald Trump hosts a meeting with business leaders in the Roosevelt
            Room of the White House in Washington January 23, 2017. REUTERS/Kevin Lamarque
            (Copyright Reuters 2017)</media>
        <p>Personal attorneys working for President Trump are weighing possible legal action against
            the cable news network MSNBC and a private journalist for reporting a portion of the
            president’s 2005 tax returns, a move the Trump legal staff believes could have <emo
                type="verb">violated</emo> federal privacy laws, the FOX Business Network has
            learned.</p>
        <p>Trump’s tax returns were published Tuesday by DCReport.org, a website operated by David
            Cay Johnston, a Pulitzer Prize winning investigative reporter. They were simultaneously
            aired on MSNBC’s <q>The Rachel Maddow Show.</q></p>
        <p>Legal experts say any case would be a long-shot given First Amendment protections for
            journalists and an important Supreme Court precedent that dates back to the famous 1971
                <q>Pentagon Papers</q> case. Trump would also have to show that the journalists were
            complicit in stealing his tax returns—which both Johnston and Maddow have denied.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="u_rep">Trump’s lawyers could try and sue but they will get the crap
                kicked out of them in court,</quote> said veteran white collar attorney Stanley
            Arkin. <quote sex="m" pol="u_rep">It’s the First Amendment. What are they going to sue
                them for? Stealing the returns? Nobody made any money out of it. Nobody was
                bribed.</quote></p>
        <p>White House spokeswoman Hope Hicks would neither confirm nor deny the president’s
            interest in a possible lawsuit against MSNBC or Johnston.</p>
        <p>In a statement, MSNBC told FOX Business: <quote sex="u" pol="u_dem">There is no legal
                prohibition against journalists publishing these tax returns. It is protected by the
                First Amendment and Supreme Court precedent.</quote></p>
        <p>Johnston, who obtained the tax documents before appearing on MSNBC, wrote a biography
            called <q>The Making of Donald Trump</q> in 2016 and won the Pulitzer Prize at The New
            York Times for <emo type="verb">exposing</emo> loopholes and inequities in the U.S. tax
            code. He didn’t respond to emails or telephone calls for comment. During the MSNBC
            broadcast, Johnston said he received Trump’s tax documents anonymously through the
            mail.</p>
        <p>Trump, a billionaire real estate <emo type="noun">mogul</emo> with business interests
            around world, has refused to release his tax returns, citing an ongoing audit by the
            Internal Revenue Service. The move has been <emo type="adj">controversial</emo> since it
            broke from recent protocol dating back to the presidency of Richard Nixon in which
            presidents released their tax returns to disclose possible conflicts of interest.</p>
        <p>Democrats in Congress have claimed that a full airing of Trump’s tax returns could show
            conflicts involving his real estate and branding <emo type="noun">empire</emo> and his
            White House dealings.</p>
        <p>Trump maintains no such conflicts exist now that he has handed over operational duties of
            the Trump Organization to his sons, Eric and Donald Jr.</p>
        <p>The 2005 tax documents aired by MSNBC and published by Johnston, however, provided no
            evidence to substantiate possible conflict of interest claims; the two pages of Trump’s
            1040 tax forms showed <emo type="adj">little</emo> more than that Trump earned $153
            million in income in 2005, and paid $38 million in taxes.</p>
        <p>In fact, some political commentators have suggested that Trump himself leaked the forms
            because they portrayed his tax issues in a relatively positive light, namely that he
            made a lot of money and paid an effective tax rate of 24%, which is higher than what
            former President Obama paid in 2015 and even what large corporations pay to the
            government.</p>
        <p>Still, people close to President Trump say he was <emo type="verb">incensed</emo> by
            their release, believing possibly that the documents were stolen, and that Johnston and
            MSNBC should not have aired what he believes to be illegally obtained personal
            information.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday morning, Trump tweeted out: </p>
        <p>After another MSNBC host, Joe Scarborough, suggested Trump himself leaked out the
            documents, Trump’s personal attorney Michael Cohen tweeted:</p>
        <p>Later that day, the president told Fox News host Tucker Carlson: <quote sex="m" pol="rep"
                >I have no idea where they got it but it’s illegal and they’re not supposed to have
                it and it's not supposed to be leaked…It’s certainly not an embarrassing tax return
                at all, but it’s an illegal thing they’ve been doing it, they’ve done it before and
                I think it’s a disgrace.</quote></p>
        <p>During the presidential campaign, The New York Times published a portion of Trump’s 1995
            New York State tax returns, which showed then candidate Trump took a $916 million loss
            on his taxes that year. The <emo type="adj">large</emo> loss would have allowed Trump to
            cancel the same level of taxable income over nearly the next two decades. Marc Kasowitz,
            an attorney for Trump, wrote The Times that it was illegal to publish the returns, but
            no lawsuit was filed.</p>
        <p>People with knowledge of the matter say Cohen is now at the center of the debate over
            whether to file a lawsuit for the latest tax disclosures. Cohen would neither confirm
            nor deny whether he and Trump are contemplating a lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Legal experts say one federal law at the center of possible legal action would be the
            Unauthorized Disclosure of Information Act, which makes it illegal to publish an
            unauthorized tax return or <q>return information</q> without receiving authorization
            from the individual whose taxes are being reported on.</p>
        <p>According to the federal statute, any violation of the law <quote sex="m" pol="u_rep"
                >shall be punishable by a fine not exceeding $5,000 or imprisonment of up to five
                years</quote>.</p>
        <p>Still, various First Amendment precedents protect journalists from such sanctions. In
            1971, the US Supreme Court ruled against the Nixon administration, which tried to stop
            The New York Times and other news outlets from publishing the so-called Pentagon Papers,
            which were a classified government study of US involvement in Vietnam.</p>
        <p>In the landmark ruling, the court said the government needed to show a heavy burden of
            proof to upend the First Amendment and stop the publication of the documents involving
            the machinations of public officials.</p>
        <p>Legal experts tell FOX Business that other precedents would <emo type="verb">shield</emo>
            journalists from legal action unless reporters were directly involved in a theft of the
            tax documents, which Johnston has denied. In fact, Columbia Law School Professor John
            Coffee said if Trump went ahead with a lawsuit, he could end up in the same position as
            Richard Nixon was in in 1971 during the release of the Pentagon Papers.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="u_dem">MSNBC is in the same position as The New York Times</quote>,
            if Trump sues as the president, Coffee said. <quote sex="m" pol="u_dem">If Trump sues as
                an individual, he will then be subject to discovery and depositions, which he will
                not like</quote>.</p>
    </body>
</article>
