<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../articleRefGuide/newsAnalysisRelax-NG.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="CNN">
            <hyperlink>http://www.cnn.com/2017/04/06/politics/donald-trump-syria-military/</hyperlink>
            <section>politics</section>
            <titleLine>Trump launches military strike against Syria</titleLine>
            <pubInfo>
                <date when="2017-04-07">2017-04-07</date>
                <time value="04:59:00">04:59:00</time>
                <!-- PM -->
                <credit>
                    <author>Barbara Starr, Jeremy Diamond</author>
                </credit>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>(CNN)The United States launched a military strike Thursday on a Syrian government airbase
            in response to a <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/04/04/middleeast/idlib-syria-attack/"
                >chemical weapons attack</a> that killed dozens of civilians earlier in the
            week.</p>
        <p>On President Donald Trump's orders, US warships launched 59 Tomahawk cruise missiles at
            the airbase that was home to the warplanes that carried out the chemical attacks, US
            officials said.</p>
        <p><a
                href="http://edition.cnn.com/2017/04/07/world/syria-military-strikes-donald-trump-russia/index.html"
                >Latest: Russia <emo type="verb">condemns</emo> Syria missile strike ordered by
                Trump</a></p>
        <p>The strike is the first direct military action taken by the US against the regime of
            Syrian President Bashar al-Assad in the country's six-year <a
                href="http://www.cnn.com/2013/08/27/world/meast/syria-civil-war-fast-facts/">civil
                war</a>. It represents a <emo type="adj">substantial</emo>
            <emo type="noun">escalation</emo> of the US military campaign in the region, and could
            be interpreted by the Syrian government as an act of war.</p>
        <p>Six people were killed in the airstrike, according to a televised statement by the
            Syrian's Armed Forces General Command. Russia <emo type="verb">condemned</emo> the
            strike as an <quote sex="m" pol="u_dem">act of aggression,</quote> and Assad's office
            Friday called it <quote sex="m" pol="u_dem">a disgraceful act</quote> that <quote
                sex="m" pol="u_dem">can only be described as short-sighted.</quote></p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">Tonight, I ordered a targeted military strike on the air field
                in Syria from where the chemical attack was launched,</quote> Trump said during
            short remarks to reporters at Mar-a-Lago, where he ordered the strike just hours
            earlier. <quote sex="m" pol="rep">It is in this vital national security of the United
                States to prevent and deter the spread and use of deadly chemical
            weapons.</quote></p>
        <p>He added: <quote sex="m" pol="rep">There can be no dispute that Syria used banned
                chemical weapons, violated its obligations under the Chemical Weapons Convention and
                ignored the urging of the UN Security Council. Years of previous attempts at
                changing Assad's behavior have all failed and failed very dramatically.</quote></p>
        <media>Video shows gas attack aftermath 01:23</media>
        <subHead>Shift in policy</subHead>
        <p>Trump's decision marked a <emo type="adj">dramatic</emo> shift in his position on whether
            the US should take military action against the Syrian President's regime -- which Trump
            opposed during his campaign for president -- and came after the President was visibly
            and publicly moved by the images of this week's chemical weapons attack.</p>
        <media>US warships launch cruise missiles at Syria 00:33</media>
        <p>The strike took place at 8:40 p.m. ET (3:40 a.m. local time), when there would have been
            minimal activity at the base. It targeted aircraft, aircraft shelters, petroleum and
            logistical storage, ammunition supply bunkers, air defense systems, and <quote sex="m"
                pol="u_rep">the things that make the airfield operate,</quote> Pentagon spokesman
            Capt. Jeff Davis told reporters. The missiles were launched from warships in the Eastern
            Mediterranean.</p>
        <p><a
                href="http://money.cnn.com/2017/04/06/investing/oil-prices-syria-us-military-action/index.html"
                >Oil prices <emo type="verb">leap</emo> after US missile strike on Syria</a></p>
        <p><quote sex="u" pol="u_rep">Initial indications are that this strike has severely damaged
                or destroyed Syrian aircraft and support infrastructure and equipment at Shayrat
                Airfield, reducing the Syrian government's ability to deliver chemical
                weapons,</quote> the Pentagon said in a statement.</p>
        <p>A US defense official told CNN Friday morning that an initial battle damage assessment
            from the strike was that 58 of the 59 missiles <quote sex="u" pol="u_rep">severely
                degraded or destroyed</quote> their intended target. The official cautioned that
            this is just the earliest assessment using radar and that more robust assessments using
            satellites and other surveillance is still pending.</p>
        <p>Thirty-six of the Tomahawks were fired from the USS Ross and the other 23 were launched
            from the USS Porter, the official added.</p>
        <p>Briefing reporters late Thursday night, Secretary of State Rex Tillerson said that the
            strike did not represent a <quote sex="m" pol="rep">change in our policy or our posture
                in Syria,</quote> even though it marked the first time the US had decided to take
            military action against the Syrian government.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">There has been no change in that status,</quote> he said. <quote
                sex="m" pol="rep">It does demonstrate that President Trump is willing to act when
                governments and actors cross the line ... and cross the line in the most heinous of
                ways.</quote></p>
        <p>Tillerson said the administration felt the strike was <quote sex="m" pol="rep"
                >proportional because it was targeted at the facility that delivered this most
                recent chemical attack.</quote></p>
        <p>The US military on Thursday showed reporters an image of the radar track of a Syrian
            airplane leaving the airfield and flying to the chemical strike area Tuesday. A second
            image of bomb damage craters at the airbase was also shown to reporters at the
            Pentagon.</p>
        <p>Tillerson said the US has a <quote sex="m" pol="rep">very high level of
                confidence</quote> that the Syrian regime carried out at least three attacks in
            recent weeks -- including on Tuesday -- using Sarin and nerve gas.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Tillerson told reporters that the administration is monitoring Syria's
            response <quote sex="m" pol="rep">in terms of whether they attack our forces or
                coalition forces</quote> or if they seek to launch another chemical weapons
            attack.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">This particular strike that was carried out on the air base from
                which the chemical weapons attack was launched was very deliberately considered by
                the President,</quote> Tillerson said. <quote sex="m" pol="rep">It is a response
                that we believe to be both proportional and appropriate.</quote></p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">The future will be guided by how we see their reaction,</quote>
            he added.</p>
        <media>Rubio hails Syria strikes, says Russians don't have standing to criticize</media>
        <p>A senior administration official told CNN Friday that the strike should not be
            interpreted as the beginning of a wider campaign to weaken or remove Assad, but instead
            is aimed at dealing with the <q>unacceptability</q> of Assad's use of chemical
            weapons.</p>
        <p>This official said the President's order to his national security team to develop a plan
            for defeating ISIS remains the priority for the administration. That strategy is
            actually well on its way to being completed, the official added.</p>
        <p>But the strikes represented not only an <emo type="noun">escalation</emo> of the US role
            in Syria, but could have a ripple effect on the US' relations with the Syrian regime's
                <emo type="adj">powerful</emo> backer, Russia.</p>
        <p>Russians were present at the base the US struck, a US defense official said, though the
            role of those Russians was not immediately known.</p>
        <p>Tillerson confirmed that the US military contacted their Russian counterparts about the
            attack ahead of time, in accordance with deconfliction policies between the US and
            Russia over military activities in Syria. Russia was given a one-hour notice, according
            to a senior US official.</p>
        <p>Russian President Vladimir Putin described the US airstrikes on Syria as <quote sex="m"
                pol="u_rep">an act of aggression against a sovereign state</quote> that <quote
                sex="m" pol="u_rep">dealt a serious blow to Russia-US relations,</quote> according
            to a Kremlin statement. Russia said it believed Syria had destroyed all of its chemical
            weapons and the US strikes were based on a <q>far-fetched pretext.</q></p>
        <subHead>Congressional reaction</subHead>
        <p><a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/04/06/politics/trump-congress-syria/index.html"
                >Lawmakers in the US generally supported</a> Trump's decision to <emo type="verb"
                >strike</emo> back against Assad Thursday night, but cautioned the President against
            unilaterally starting a war without first consulting Congress.</p>
        <p>A pair of defense hawks -- Sens. John McCain and Lindsey Graham -- who have <emo
                type="adv">frequently</emo> been critical of Trump, <emo type="adv">roundly</emo>
            <emo type="verb">praised</emo> his decision Thursday night.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">Acting on the orders of their commander-in-chief, they have sent
                an important message the United States will no longer stand idly by as Assad, aided
                and abetted by Putin's Russia, slaughters innocent Syrians with chemical weapons and
                barrel bombs,</quote> McCain and Graham said in a joint statement.</p>
        <media>Rubio: Russia should be embarrassed, ashamed 01:16</media>
        <p>But Sen. Rand Paul called on Trump to consult on Congress.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">While we all condemn the atrocities in Syria, the United States
                was not attacked,</quote> Paul said. <quote sex="m" pol="rep">The President needs
                congressional authorization for military action as required by the Constitution, and
                I call on him to come to Congress for a proper debate.</quote></p>
        <p>The US began launching airstrikes in Syria in September 2014 under President Barack Obama
            as part of its coalition campaign against ISIS, but has only targeted the terrorist
            group and not Syrian government forces.</p>
        <subHead>The order</subHead>
        <p>Trump met with his national security team before his dinner with Chinese President Xi
            Jinping in Mar-a-Lago Thursday, where he made the decision to pull the trigger on the
            biggest military action of his presidency, national security adviser H.R. McMaster
            said.</p>
        <p>He sat through dinner with Xi as the action was under way.</p>
        <p>The decision came two days after he was <q>immediately notified</q> of the chemical
            attack in Syria and asked his team to determine who was responsible. After it became
            clear Assad was responsible, Trump asked his team to develop options -- and settled on
            one Thursday after <quote sex="m" pol="rep">a meeting of considerable length and
                far-reaching discussion,</quote> McMaster told reporters.</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary James Mattis has been updating Trump about the missile strikes in Syria
            following his dinner with Xi, according to a US official.</p>
        <p>Mattis, Tillerson and McMaster were with Trump at Mar-a-Lago at the time. Vice President
            Mike Pence remained in Washington, where he returned to the White House after
            dinner.</p>
        <p>Trump's order to strike the Syrian government targets came a day after he said the
            chemical attacks -- whose <emo type="adj">grisly</emo> effects were broadcast worldwide
            where videos captured in the immediate aftermath -- <quote sex="m" pol="rep">crossed a
                lot of lines for me</quote> and said he felt a <quote sex="m" pol="rep"
                >responsibility</quote> to respond.</p>
        <media>Tillerson: No doubt Assad is responsible 01:39</media>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">I will tell you it's already happened that my attitude toward
                Syria and Assad has changed very much,</quote> Trump said.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">When you kill innocent children -- innocent babies -- babies --
                little babies with a chemical gas that is so lethal, people were shocked to hear
                what gas it was, that crosses many, many lines. Beyond a red line, many, many
                lines,</quote> Trump said.</p>
        <subHead><q>Red line</q></subHead>
        <p>Trump's decision to launch the strikes, the most <emo type="adj">significant</emo>
            military action of his young presidency, came nearly four years after the US first
            concluded that Syrian forces had used chemical weapons in Syria.</p>
        <p>The Obama administration concluded that Syria had violated the <q>red line</q> Obama had
            set a year earlier in discussing the use of chemical weapons, but ultimately decided
            against military action against Syria in favor of a Russian-brokered deal to extricate
            the country's chemical weapons <emo type="noun">stockpile</emo>.</p>
        <p> Trump at the time said the US should <quote sex="m" pol="rep">stay the hell out of
                Syria</quote> and urged Obama on Twitter to <quote sex="m" pol="rep">not attack
                Syria</quote> in the wake of the 2013 chemical attack.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="u_rep">There is no upside and tremendous downside. Save your
                    <q>powder</q> for another (and more important) day,</quote> he tweeted in
            September 2013.</p>
        <p>Trump repeatedly criticized Obama during his presidential campaign for not acting on his
                <q>red line</q> threat, but the real estate <emo type="noun">mogul</emo> also <emo
                type="verb">argued</emo> against deepening the US' military involvement in Syria,
            particularly as it related to Assad.</p>
        <p>Trump argued last May in a TV interview that he would <quote sex="m" pol="u_rep">go after
                ISIS big league,</quote> but said he did not support targeting Assad's regime,
            arguing the US has <quote sex="m" pol="u_rep">bigger problems than Assad.</quote></p>
        <p>Syria's six-year civil war has claimed the lives of at least 400,000, according to a
            United Nations estimate released a year ago. More than 5 million Syrians have fled the
            country and more than 6 million more have been displaced internally, according to UN
            agencies.</p>
        <subHead>2016 rhetoric</subHead>
        <p>But guided by his <q>America First</q> ideology and rejection of the US' propensity for
                <q>nation-building,</q> Trump did not <emo type="verb">argue</emo> in favor of
            stepped-up US intervention during his campaign for president.</p>
        <media> Hillary Clinton: US should take out Assad's air fields</media>
        <p>Instead, he signaled the opposite: He <emo type="verb">argued</emo> that the US should
            remain laser-focused on defeating ISIS and <emo type="noun">vowed</emo> to try and
            partner with Russia, which has <emo type="adv">heartily</emo> backed Assad's regime, in
            order to defeat ISIS and bring the conflict to an end.</p>
        <p>Those views appeared <emo type="verb">steeped</emo> in his longstanding criticism of the
            Iraq War, which he called a <quote sex="m" pol="rep">stupid</quote> decision, <emo
                type="verb">lamenting</emo> the billions of dollars funneled toward that war effort
            instead of on domestic programs, like infrastructure spending.</p>
        <p>While Trump <emo type="verb">rejected</emo> the isolationist label some placed on him
            during the campaign, he made clear that his preference was for limiting the US footprint
            around the world and refocusing US foreign policy around core national security
            interests.</p>
    </body>
</article>
