<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../articleRefGuide/newsAnalysisRelax-NG.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="NPR">
            <hyperlink>http://www.npr.org/2017/04/06/522948481/u-s-launches-airstrikes-against-syria-after-chemical-attack</hyperlink>
            <section>politics</section>
            <titleLine>Trump Orders Syria Airstrikes After <q>Assad Choked Out The Lives</q> Of
                Civilians</titleLine>
            <pubInfo>
                <date when="2017-04-06">2017-04-06</date>
                <time value="09:37:00">09:37:00</time>
                <!-- PM -->
                <credit>
                    <author>Mari Katkov, Jessica Taylor, Tom Bowman</author>
                </credit>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>President Trump has launched airstrikes in Syria in response to deadly chemical attacks
            allegedly ordered by the country's president, Bashar Assad, against his own people.</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">Tonight I ordered a targeted military strike on the airfield in
                Syria from where the chemical attack was launched,</quote> the president announced
            Thursday night from his Mar-a-Lago resort in Palm Beach, Fla., where he is meeting with
            Chinese President Xi Jinping. <quote sex="m" pol="rep">It is in this vital national
                security interest of the United States to prevent and deter the spread and use of
                deadly chemical weapons.</quote></p>
        <p>The decision to launch airstrikes Thursday evening was a <emo type="noun">departure</emo>
            for Trump, who has been slow to <emo type="verb">embrace</emo> an interventionist
            foreign policy. The chemical attack has been seen as a <a
                href="http://www.npr.org/2017/04/05/522704455/after-syria-gas-attack-world-awaits-what-kind-of-leader-trump-will-be"
                >key test of Trump's leadership</a> on the world <emo type="noun">stage</emo>.</p>
        <media>The guided-missile destroyer USS Porter transits the Mediterranean Sea on March 9.
            The more than 50 Tomahawk missile strikes were carried out against Shayrat air base in
            Homs province from the USS Porter and USS Ross in the Eastern Mediterranean. Seaman Ford
            Williams/U.S. Navy</media>
        <p>The U.S. fired 59 Tomahawk missiles from the USS Porter and USS Ross destroyers in the
            Eastern Mediterranean against the Shayrat air base, where the U.S. says the planes that
            carried out a chemical weapons attack originated. The missiles targeted aircraft and
            aircraft shelters, ammunition, air defense systems and radars.</p>
        <p>U.S. officials said planners did everything possible to avoid civilian casualties and are
            still doing battle damage assessment to determine the exact results of the raid.</p>
        <subHead>Moscow says strike violates international law</subHead>
        <p>Russia was warned in multiple conversations that this air base was going to be targeted,
            officials said. There were Russians at the base. Russian President Vladimir Putin has
            called the idea that Assad was behind the attacks simply <quote sex="m" pol="u_rep"
                >groundless accusations.</quote></p>
        <p>Kremlin spokesman Dmitry Peskov, in his regular Friday morning briefing, said the U.S.
            strike constituted <quote sex="m" pol="u_rep">aggression against a sovereign state in
                violation of international law.</quote></p>
        <p>Peskov said Russian President Vladimir Putin believed the strike was based on a
                <q>made-up pretext</q> to distract attention from civilian deaths in Iraq, an <emo
                type="adj">apparent</emo> reference to U.S. airstrikes in Mosul.</p>
        <p>Yet Trump said Thursday night that <quote sex="m" pol="rep">there can be no dispute that
                Syria used banned chemical weapons, violated its obligations under the Chemical
                Weapons Convention and ignored the urging of the U.N. Security Council.</quote> He
            concluded his statement by saying:</p>
        <media>Map showing major cities in Syria</media>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">Tonight I call on all civilized nations to join us in seeking to
                end the slaughter and bloodshed in Syria and also to end terrorism of all kinds and
                all types. We ask for God's wisdom as we face the challenge of our very troubled
                world. We pray for the lives of the wounded and for the souls of those who passed.
                And we hope that as long as America stands for justice, that peace and harmony will,
                in the end, prevail.</quote></p>
        <p>The chemical attacks earlier this week killed more than 100 Syrians, including many
            children. On Wednesday, Trump said that the attacks <quote sex="m" pol="rep">crossed a
                lot of lines for me</quote> and hinted that he might pursue some sort of military
            action in response.</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Rex Tillerson told reporters in Florida after the president spoke that
            they had a <quote sex="m" pol="rep">very high level of confidence that the attacks were
                carried out under aircraft under the direction of [Assad's] regime</quote> and a
                <quote sex="m" pol="rep">very high confidence that the attacks involved the use of
                sarin nerve gas.</quote></p>
        <p>White House national security adviser H.R. McMaster said at the briefing that the
            military planners took <quote sex="m" pol="rep">great pains</quote> to avoid risk to
                <quote sex="m" pol="rep">third country nationals at that airport — I think you read
                Russians from that.</quote></p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">We weighed the risk associated with any military action, but we
                weighed that against the risk of inaction ... which is the risk of [these] continued
                egregious, inhumane attacks on innocent civilians with chemical weapons.</quote></p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">There were measures put in place to avoid hitting what we
                believe is a storage of sarin ... [so] that it would not be ignited and cause a
                hazard to civilians or anyone else.</quote></p>
        <p>In his initial response to the Syrian attacks on Tuesday, Trump cast <emo type="noun"
                >blame</emo> on former President Barack Obama for failing to act enough on the
            situation and engaging after Assad first crossed the <q>red line</q> Obama drew
            following Assad's use of chemical weapons in 2013.</p>
        <p>But, as NPR's Tamara Keith <a
                href="http://www.npr.org/2017/04/04/522627064/on-the-record-president-trump-vs-private-citizen-trump-on-syria"
                >noted</a>, Trump himself had argued then as a private citizen that the U.S. should
            not become engaged in the conflict.</p>
        <p>Here are the president's full remarks from Thursday night:</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">On Tuesday Syrian President Bashar al-Assad launched a horrible
                chemical attack on innocent civilians using a deadly nerve agent. Assad choked out
                the lives of helpless men, women and children. It was a slow and brutal death for so
                many. Even beautiful babies were cruelly murdered at this very barbaric attack. No
                child of God should ever suffer such horror. Tonight I ordered a targeted military
                strike on the airfield in Syria from where the chemical attack was launched. It is
                in this vital national security interest of the United States to prevent and deter
                the spread and use of deadly chemical weapons. There can be no dispute that Syria
                used banned chemical weapons, violated its obligations under the Chemical Weapons
                Convention and ignored the urging of the U.N. Security Council. Numerous previous
                attempts at changing Assad's behavior have all failed, and failed very dramatically.
                As a result, the refugee crisis continues to deepen and the region continues to
                destabilize, threatening the United States and its allies. Tonight I call on all
                civilized nations to join us in seeking to end the slaughter and bloodshed in Syria
                and also to end terrorism of all kinds and all types. We ask for God's wisdom as we
                face the challenge of our very troubled world. We pray for the lives of the wounded
                and for the souls of those who passed. And we hope that as long as America stands
                for justice, that peace and harmony will, in the end, prevail. Good night and God
                bless America and the entire world.</quote></p>
        <subHead>Congressional reaction is mixed</subHead>
        <p>House Intelligence Committee ranking member Adam Schiff, D-Calif., said the president
            needs to coordinate any future action with Congress:</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="dem">This strike will not hasten an end to the Assad regime, but it
                may deter its further use of chemical weapons. Nevertheless. this missile strike and
                the military action of our forces already in Syria have yet to be authorized by
                Congress. I will be reintroducing an authorization for use of military force against
                ISIS and al-Qaida when Congress returns to session. Congress cannot abdicate its
                responsibility any longer and should vote on any use of force not made in
                self-defense.</quote></p>
        <p>House Foreign Affairs Committee Chairman Ed Royce, R-Calif., agreed:</p>
        <p><quote sex="m" pol="rep">Assad was warned, repeatedly, by the U.S. and the U.N. that the
                intentional targeting of innocent men, women and children is intolerable. Now Assad
                has been caught red-handed carrying out another abhorrent chemical attack, and the
                administration has taken a measured response. Moving ahead, the administration must
                work with Congress and lay out clear policy goals for Syria and the
            region.</quote></p>
    </body>
</article>
