<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../articleRefGuide/newsAnalysisRelax-NG.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<article>
    <head>
        <siteInfo ref="NPR">
            <hyperlink>http://www.npr.org/sections/parallels/2017/01/27/511861645/trumps-immigration-freeze-omits-those-linked-to-deadly-attacks-in-u-s</hyperlink>
            <section>POLITICS &amp; POLICY</section>
            <titleLine>Trump's Immigration Freeze Omits Those Linked To Deadly Attacks In U.S.</titleLine>
            <pubInfo>
                <date>January 27, 2017</date>
                <time>1:32 PM ET</time>
                <credit>
                    <author>GREG MYRE</author>
                </credit>
            </pubInfo>
        </siteInfo>
    </head>
<body>
    <media>Protesters hold signs near the White House during a protest about President Trump's immigration policies on Wednesday. A proposed presidential action would freeze immigration from seven mostly Muslim countries for security reasons. But the list does not include any of the countries whose nationals have killed Americans in the U.S. since Sept. 11, 2001.
Alex Brandon/AP</media>

<update>Updated 2 p.m. ET</update>

<p>President Trump's freeze on immigration from seven mostly Muslim countries cites the potential threat of terrorism. But here's the <emo type="noun">twist</emo> — it doesn't include any countries from which radicalized Muslims have actually killed Americans in the U.S. since Sept. 11, 2001.</p>

<p>The president's executive action, which he signed Friday at the Pentagon, applies to these countries: Syria, Iran, Libya, Somalia, Yemen, Iraq and Sudan.</p>

<p>Yet no Muslim extremist from any of these places has carried out a <emo type="adv">fatal</emo> <emo type="verb">attack</emo> in the U.S. in more than two decades.</p>

<p>In contrast, here are the countries of origin of radicalized Muslims who carried out deadly attacks in the U.S., beginning on Sept. 11, 2001: Saudi Arabia, Egypt, Lebanon, United Arab Emirates, Pakistan, Russia and Kyrgyzstan.</p>

<p>The two lists are <emo type="adj">completely</emo> <emo type="adj">distinct</emo>, raising questions about the reasoning behind the White House plan.</p>

    <p><quote>These seven countries were identified by the Obama Administration as needing further travel scrutiny,</quote> White House press secretary Sean Spicer said Sunday on ABC's <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/spicer-trump/story?id=45123887">This Week</a>. <quote>There are 46 other countries with Muslim populations that are not part of this and I think that's an important thing to note.</quote></p>

<p>But there were many critics.</p>

    <p><quote>I think this is an overreaction,</quote> says <a href="http://kurzman.unc.edu/">Charles Kurzman</a>, a sociology professor at the University of North Carolina, <a href="https://sites.duke.edu/tcths/files/2017/01/Kurzman_Muslim-American_Involvement_in_Violent_Extremism_2016.pdf">who has tracked</a> Muslim extremism in the U.S. for years.</p>

    <p><quote>We just haven't seen a large number of Muslim-Americans answering the call to revolutionary violence that the self-proclaimed Islamic State and other groups have been pitching at them,</quote> he adds.</p>

<p>The nations on the White House list include several mired in civil wars, as well as those that host extremist groups. All have had fraught relations with the U.S. American drones or warplanes have conducted airstrikes in five of the seven.</p>

    <p>The executive action read: <q>Deteriorating conditions in certain countries due to war, strife, disaster, and civil unrest increase the likelihood that terrorists will use any means possible to enter our country.</q></p>

    <subHead>Existing visa restrictions</subHead>

<p>Citizens from the seven nations in Trump's order already faced <emo type="adj">great</emo> difficulty in obtaining visas, gaining refugee status or immigrating to the U.S.</p>

    <p><quote>The U.S. immigration vetting system is extremely thorough. That is perhaps why we've seen so little violence by immigrants and refugees in the United States,</quote> said Kurzman. <quote>As someone who brings over international students, international scholars for conferences and training programs, I know how hard it is to get even extremely upright folks through that system.</quote></p>

<p>The 19 terrorists on the hijacked planes used in the Sept. 11 attacks were from four countries not on the new White House list: Saudi Arabia, Egypt, Lebanon and the United Arab Emirates.</p>

    <p>Since then, radicalized Muslims have carried out a number of deadly attacks in the U.S. The precise count varies among groups that track the terror threat, but most groups cite fewer than 10 lethal attacks and fewer than 100 deaths, including <a href="https://www.newamerica.org/in-depth/terrorism-in-america/what-threat-united-states-today/">New America</a>, a nonpartisan think tank in Washington.</p>

<p>The deadliest single attack was at the Pulse nightclub in Orlando last June, which left 49 dead. The man responsible was Omar Mateen, whose parents were from Afghanistan, though he was born in New York. Afghanistan is not on the White House list.</p>

<p>In a few cases, foreign-born nationals have carried out <emo type="adj">lethal</emo> attacks.</p>

<p>They include Tashfeen Malik, who, along with her husband, was responsible for the San Bernardino, Calif., shooting that claimed 14 lives in December 2015. She was born in Pakistan but spent most of her life in Saudi Arabia until she came to the U.S. in 2014 on a fiancée visa to marry Syed Rizwan Farook. He was born in Chicago, to a family originally from Pakistan. Neither Pakistan nor Saudi Arabia are on the White House list.</p>

<p>Similarly, the Boston Marathon bombing was carried out by two brothers, Tamerlan and Dzhokar Tsarnaev. Tamerlan was born in the Soviet Union (now southern Russia), and Dzhokar was born in Krygyzstan. Those countries are not on the White House list.</p>

<subHead>Here's a list of attacks linked to radicalized Muslims in the U.S. since the Sept. 11, 2001, attacks:</subHead>

<p>2016	Omar Mateen shot dead 49 at the Pulse nightclub in Orlando. His parents were originally from Afghanistan. He was born in New York.</p>

<p>2015	Syed Rizwan Farook and his wife Tashfeen Malik shot dead 14 people at an office in San Bernardino, Ca., before they were killed. He was born in Chicago to parents from Pakistan. She was born in Pakistan and raised mostly in Saudi Arabia.</p>

<p>2015	Mohammad Abdulazeez opened fire at two military recruiting centers in Chattanooga, Tenn., killing five U.S. military personnel. He was a naturalized American who was born in Kuwait to parents who were Jordanian and Palestinian.</p>

<p>2013	Two brothers, Tamerlan and Dzhokhar Tsarnaev carried out the Boston Marathon bombing that killed three. Tamerlan was born in the Soviet Union (now southern Russia), and Dzokhar was born in Kyrgyzstan.</p>

<p>2009	Army Maj. Nidal Hasan, shot dead 13 in Ft. Hood, Texas. Hasan, who was born in Virginia to Palestinian parents who had immigrated from the West Bank, has been sentenced to the death penalty.</p>

<p>2009	Abdulhakim Muhammad shot and killed an Army private at a recruiting center in Little Rock. He was born in Memphis to a Christian family, but converted to Islam and changed his name from Carlos Bledsoe.</p>

<p>2002	Egyptian national Hesham Hadayet shot dead two Israelis at the El Al airline ticket counter at the Los Angeles Airport before being killed.</p>
</body>
</article>